Guide to the Department of African and African American Studies records, 1966-1981 UA.25.06.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Department of African and African American Studies records
1966-1981
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Department of African and African American Studies
UA.25.06.0001
3 Linear Feet
The Dept. of African and African American Studies collection contains the office files of department directors Walter Burford and William Turner. Materials and topics in the collection include course materials for courses taught under the aegis of Black Studies' instructors; the large efforts channeled into recruitment of full-time faculty for the program; committee work related to Black Studies proposals and to the program's departmental status; budgets; and printed matter relating to similar programs and problems at other schools. The materials date from 1966-1981.
2,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Department of African and African American Studies records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1976, 1983, 1986.
Historical Note
The initiative for the establishment of the Department of African and African American Studies began in October of 1968 when at an ad hoc meeting called by Dean William Griffith (at the request of the President of the University) Duke's Afro-American Society presented 12 demands. One of these demands called for the establishment of a Black Studies Program consisting of courses on Afro-American History, socio-economics, community development, black arts, black people in American politics, Afro-American literature, etc. Although there appeared to be general receptiveness to the proposition of a Black Studies Program, concern was expressed by some administrators present that "'funding and the ability to secure competent teachers' might present an obstacle to formation of the program." After a few meetings the momentum for the creation of Black Studies Program staled.
On February 13, 1969 sixty members of the Afro-American Society occupied the Allen Building (the main administrative building on campus) for eight hours and presented the university administration with a list of thirteen demands. The demands once again included the "establishment of a fully-accredited department of Afro-American Studies."
In response to the Allen Building Takeover the administration met with the Afro- American Society and accepted 12 of their 13 points. Following this acceptance the Supervisory Committee on Black Studies chaired by Louis Budd of the English Department was formed. The composition of the committee was contested by the students who demanded equal representation among the faculty and students. The final composition of the committee, however, was 5 faculty members and 3 students.
In May 1969, the Black Studies Committee submitted and received approval for the Black Studies Program from the Undergraduate Faculty Council of the Arts and Sciences (UFCAS). Walter Burford was named program head in 1970. Since its creation the program and eventually department has undergone various name changes. Some previous names include Black Studies Program, Afro-American Studies, African and Afro-American Studies, and its most recent (2007) incarnation African and African American Studies.
For a more in depth history of the department until 1984 please consult Report of Ad Hoc Committee on African and Afro-American Studies located in the Black History at Duke Reference Collection.
Collection Overview
Collection contains the office files of the Director of African and African American Studies. Materials and topics in the collection include course materials for courses taught under the aegis of Black Studies' instructors; the large efforts channeled into recruitment of full-time faculty for the program; committee work related to Black Studies proposals and to the program's departmental status; budgets; information concerning similar programs and problems at other schools; and printed material received by the office which gives something of the flavor of minority affairs and resources around the country. Two 7-inch magnetic tape reels are also present documenting the 1972 Black Religion Symposium. The materials date from 1966-1981.
Related Material
African Studies Committee Records
University Archives, Duke University
Allen Building Takeover Collection, 1969-2002
University Archives, Duke University
Black History at Duke Reference Collection, 1948-2001 and undated
University Archives, Duke University
Black Student Alliance Records, 1969-2006
University Archives, Duke University
Edgar Tristram Thompson papers, 1915-1985
University Archives, Duke University
Sound recordings; Students, Black -- North Carolina; Race relations; Student participation in administration; Blacks -- Historiography; College students, Black -- North Carolina; African Americans -- Historiography; Blacks -- Study and teaching; Clippings (information artifacts); African American students -- North Carolina -- Durham; African Americans -- Study and teaching; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; Duke University -- History; Duke University. Afro-American Society; Duke University. Office of Black Studies
- Department of African and African American Studies records, 1966-1981, 2 boxes
  - Adams, Anne Donchin, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - African Art course, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - African-American Scholars, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Afro-American Students and Afro-American Studies, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Afro-American Studies 99, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Afro-American Studies Committee, 1976-1978 (see also Black Studies Committee) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Afro Boutique, Direct African Importer, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Allen, Samuel, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Allen, Walter, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - ASALH (Association for the Study of Afro-American Life and History) Convention 1976, Paul Robeson Film Schedule, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Association of Social and Behavioral Scientists, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bambara, Toni Cade, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Baraka, Amiri, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Barber, James. 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Battle, Joseph, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Beauchamp, Dan E., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Becton, Charles, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bibliographies, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Billings, David J., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Blackburn, John (Chancellor), 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Black in the City (NCCCEH) North Carolina Committee for Continuing Education in the Humanities, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Black Religion Symposium, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Black Seminarians Union, The (Duke University), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Black Student Alliance (Assoc. of African Studies), 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Black Student Roster, Spring 1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Black Studies, Course Descriptions and Considerations, etc., correspondence, 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Black Studies. Course Materials, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Black Studies. Course Materials, Exam, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Black Studies Committee, 1970-1979 and undated (see also Afro-American Studies Committee) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Black Studies Department. Proposals, (see also Afro-American Studies Committee; Black Studies Committee) 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Black Studies Program history (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Black Studies Programs, other schools, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Black Studies Programs, other schools, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Black Studies Symposium, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Book lists from Publishers, 1976-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bradley, David, course proposal for Religion "Black Literature in a Theological Context," 1975 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Comments on Robert S. Brown's "The Economic Case for Reparations to Black America (M. Bronfenbrenner - Kenan Professor of Economics, Duke University), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - [folder 39 removed] (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Budd, Louis, 1971; 1975 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Budget, 1971-1979 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Bulletin Materials, 1975-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Burford, Walter, (Director Black Studies Program), 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Burness, Donald (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Carson, Sonny (Mwalium Imiri Abubadika), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Carter, Howard, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Charlesworth, James H., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Chronicle News Articles, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Clarke, Austin, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Cleage, Albert, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Cleaveland, Provost Frederick, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Colton, Joel, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Cone, James, 1971, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Conferences (non-Duke), 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Conferences (non-Duke), 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence, misc., 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Curriculum vitae of staff (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - DeAlmeida, Eleanor, 1976,undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Dean's view of Central College (Pella, Iowa) (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Divinity School, Black Church Studies Center (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Everett, Chestyn (Hunger: USA) (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Faculty Recruitment, Anthropology, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Faculty Recruitment, Dept. of English, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Faculty Recruitment, Dept. of Economics, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Faculty Recruitment, Dept. of History, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Faculty Recruitment, Dept. of Philosophy, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Faculty Recruitment, Political Science, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Faculty Recruitment, Sociology, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Faculty Recruitment - Various Recruitment Documents, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Fein, John M., Dean of Trinity College, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Ferguson, Oliver, Chairman Dept. of English, 1970, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Financial Aid Budget Study, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Financial Aid Budget Study Recommendations for 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - [folder 74 removed] (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Ford Foundation Reports, Black Studies Reports, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Gavins, Raymond, Associate Professor of History, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Graduate Fellowships and Proposals, summer awards, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Greenfield, Gerald Michael, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Grove Press, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Guinier, Prof. [Chairman Afro-American Studies, Harvard], 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hampton Associates, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dr. Stephen Henderson, English candidate, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hogg, Richard, Professor Tennessee State University, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - House Courses, 1974; 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Independent Study, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Institutional Racism at Duke University, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Jackson, Blyden, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Jarrett, Nathaniel, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Jeffers, Lance, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Job Notices, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Jones, Robert E., Yale University Assistant Professor of Practical Theology, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Kerckhoff, Alan C., Chairman Department of Sociology, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - King, George, Director of Afro-American Studies, Univ. of Minnesota, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Koman, Janice, Co-Chairperson Duke Union Cable Television Project, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Langford, Thomas, Chairperson Religion Department, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Lectures, programs at Duke University, 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Lee, Carleton L., Director Black Americana Studies, Univ. of Western Michigan, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Lewis, Harold W., Dean of Faculty, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Library Acquisitions, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Library Blacklist, recent additions to the Durham City-County Library's Negro Collection, Stanford L. Warren Branch, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - [folder 27 removed] (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Mailing lists (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Memorandums outgoing, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - [folder 30 removed] (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Minority Studies and Human Rights, summer 1977 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - [folder 32 removed] (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - The National Du Sable Memorial Society, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - New York City Council Against Poverty, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - News Clippings, 1970-1972 (mostly from The Chronicle) (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - NOMMO, Africana Studies and Research Center Newsletter Purdue University, c.1977 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Oleila, Henry, Assistant Professor of Afro-American Studies, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Beyond those Hills, Henry Oleila, Mary Jane Neuendorffer, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - President's Council on Black Affairs, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Price, James (Dean) [re: name of department], 1970 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Printed Matter - miscellaneous offerings, 1975-1979 and undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Printed Matter - miscellaneous offerings, 1979-1980 and undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Provost group minutes, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Kenneth A. Pye, Acting Chancellor, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Racism at St. Peters College (Jersey City, N.J.), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Randolph, Philip A. Educational Fund (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Charles Ray, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Recruitment of Black Students, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Research Grants, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - [folder 50 removed] (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Terry Sanford, President, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Seaman, Mary, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Black Studies - Self-Study, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Shrine of the Black Madonna, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Smith, Cynthia, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Special Events, 1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Spragens, Thomas A. Curriculum Committee [re: name of program] (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Black faculty and staff at Duke University, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Student complaints, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Student Organization for Black Unity, 1970 (Greensboro, NC) (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Summer Awards, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Summer Session, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Survey Results - Black Studies Program directors at American colleges, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Teacher Course and Student Evaluations, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Teaching Materials: Chapters 1, 3, and 5 "Institutional Racism" (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Teaching Materials: Bibliographies and research guides, 1975-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Teaching Materials: Psychopathologie Africaine, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Teaching Materials: Article II, Racism and Culture (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Teaching Materials: Short Story - Orde Coobs "Silas Canterbury" (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Teaching Materials: Article I "The Significance of Africanisms" (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Thomas, Bettye, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Thorpe, Earl E., 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - 3M Company, 1972 [re: microfilm of the Schomburg Collection] (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Todd, Brecken, 1971 [re: Race and fellowships] (see also tuition awards) (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Toward a Rationale of Afro-American Studies at Princeton University (by Princeton's AASP staff), c. 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Transfer Students, 1973; 1976 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Travel Possibilities, 1972; 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Tuition Awards, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Turner, William, Acting Director Afro-American studies, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Speak in a Mourning Land by William C. Turner Jr. (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - UFCAS (Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences): Committee on Courses of Instruction, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - UFCAS (Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences): Curriculum Committee, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - UFCAS (Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences): UFCAS Executive Committee, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - UFCAS (Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences): Report to UFCAS, October 9, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Undergraduate Research Assistantship Program, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - United Mexican American Students, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - United States Commission on Civil Rights, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - United States Department of Justice, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Vesic, Aleksander, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Voices in Black Studies, National Council for Black Studies, July/September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Washington, H.R. speech at Duke University (Feb. 25, 1975), "The Criminal Justice System as a Tool of Repression: A Constitutional Overview" (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Weeber, Richard P., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Welsh, Prof., Judea Reform Congregation, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Kenny J. Williams - English, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Stenographer notebook 1 with miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Stenographer notebook 2 with miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Stenographer notebook 3 with miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Stenographer notebook 4 with miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Stenographer notebook 5 with miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Stenographer notebook 6 with miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Stenographer notebook 7 with miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Black Religion Symposium (August 8, 1972) Topic "Black Religion and Black Revolution": Speakers: Albert Cleage, Reverend, Detroit, Michigan; Nathanial Jarrett, Reverend, Yale University; Carlton Lee, Professor
    - Open reel audio tape (Box 4, Audio-reel UA25060001-RR-0001)
    - Digital audio file (Digital-materials UA25060001-SET-0001, Audio-file UA25060001-RR-0001.WAV)
  - Black Studies Master Reel 2
    - Open reel audio tape (Box 4, Audio-reel UA25060001-RR-0002)
    - Digital audio file (Digital-materials UA25060001-SET-0001, Audio-file UA25060001-RR-0002.WAV)